Guide to the Collection of Works by Arnold Wesker given to Nathaniel Tarn
Collection of works by Arnold Wesker given to Nathaniel Tarn.,
ca. 1920-1988
M1369
Tarn, Nathaniel
2 linear ft. (3 manuscript boxes + 1 print box)
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Part of the collection has been cataloged individually by monograph title. The material in this collection is more ephemeral, including texts in magazines, criticism, theater programs, posters, and a sketch.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 2002. Transferred from books, 2003. Accession # 2003-065.
Biography / Administrative History
Arnold Wesker gave a collection of his works to Nathaniel Tarn, in part because Tarn was a very thorough collector, but also to see what such a collection would eventually look like and perhaps, to ascertain at some point in the future what value would be ascribed to such a collection.
Scope and Content of Collection
Part of the collection has been cataloged individually by monograph title. The material in this collection is more ephemeral, including texts in magazines, criticism, theater programs, posters, and a sketch.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Tarn, Nathaniel.; Wesker, Arnold, 1932-; American literature--20th century.
Related Material
Part of the collection has been cataloged individually by monograph title.
Collection Contents
- Play bills and play texts, 1960 - 1980, M1369 Series 1
  - Scene 7 from a proposed musical1960 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Arts Quarterly, No. 3, London. With a doodle pasted in and an explanatory inscription to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "Festival One," Program 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Wellingborough Trades Council
  - "Tag fur Tag," ("Roots"), German translation1962, February (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Play text, Theater Huete, Weske r play. Photograph of chair pasted in .[ play set item]
  - "Chips with Everything" 1962, December (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Play text, Wesker play, Players and Plays, Vol. 10, No. 3 London
  - "Ziemniaki Do Wazysikich Dan," ("Chips with Everything"), (Polish translation)1963 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Play text, Wesker play. Dialog, Vol. 8, No. 7, Warsaw, Poland
  - "Patatas Fritas a Volunta," ("Chips with Everything") (Spanish translation)1964, August (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Play text, Wesker play, Primer Acto, No. 55, Barcelona, Spain. Two copies, each with a dfferent note to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "Los Cuatro Estaciones," ("The Four Seasons")1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Play bill. Wesker play, El Teatro Estudio, Cuba
  - "Their Very Own and Golden City"1965, September (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Play text, Wesker play. in Quest, Quarterly No. 1, London, Paul Hamblyn Publishers. Also contains two long notes to Nathaniel Tarn, and text projections for Tarn's second book, "Eagle Escaped This City."
  - "Their Very Own and Golden City" 1966, May 19 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Play bill of Wesker play, Royal Court Theatre, London
  - "La Cuisine" (French translation)1967, August (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Play text of Wesker play in L'Avant Scene, No 385, (With a note in French from Wesker to Nathaniel Tarn).
  - "Les Quatre Saisons"(French translation)1969, January (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Play text, l'Avant Scene, No. 417.
  - "The Friends"1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Play text of Wesker play, fourth draft, signature in pencil by Wesker, inscription to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - Preproduction Notes for "The Friends"1970, March (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Directional notes by Wesker for "The Friends," London production, unpublished
    The Round House
  - "The Friends"1970, October (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Play text of Wesker play in Plays and Players, Vol. 18, No. 1, London ,with photograph of donkey pasted in. (For loose photographs see Box 3) Note to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "Vannera" (Swedish translation)1971 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Play bill of Wesker play. Signature by Wesker
  - "Hora Sarutului" ("Menace for Six Sundays") (Hungarian translation)1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    Play text for television by Wesker, "Hora Sarutului." ("Menace for Six Sundays.") in Secolu 20, Revista de Literatura, Universala Bucharest ( in Hungarian ) No. 9, with photograph of Wesker as a child in Hyde Park, London pasted in. (See also loose photographs in Box 3.)
  - "Koket" ("The Kitchen") (Swedish translation)1971, September 10 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Play bill of play by Wesker, "Koket." Also notes in English from Wesker's notebook. With note and inscription to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "Los Amigos," ("The Friends") (Spanish translation)1972, January (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Play text of Wesker play, "Los Amigos" ("The Friends"), in Primer Acto, No. 140.
  - "The Friends"[1972?] (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Play bill of Wesker play, Vannerna Productions
  - "The Old Ones"1972, October (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Play text of play by Wesker, in Plays and Players, Vol. 20, No. 1, London
  - "The Old Ones"1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    One page of directional notes by Wesker for "The Old Ones"
  - "I Vecchi," ("The Old Ones") (Italian translation)n.d. (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Early version of Wesker play ,"The Old Ones", in Sapario, No. 320, Rome.
  - "The Journalists"1975 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Play text of play by Wesker, Writers and Readers Publishing Cooperative. London.
  - "Liebesbriefe auf Blauen Papier" ("Love Letters on Blue Paper") (German translation)1976 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    "Love Letters on Blue Paper," Play text of Wesker play, Berlin. Henschalverlag, Henschal Collection. With publisher's free copy form to Wesker. Inscription to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "The Wedding Feast," Parts 1 and 21977, April-May (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Play text of play by Wesker, Plays and Players, Vol. 24, No. 7, London. Inscribed to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "The Merchant"1977 - 1978 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Play text of play by Wesker, in Adam International Review, Vol. XLI,. 401-403, London. Also contains an article: "Wesker's Quest for Values" by Peter Bowering, and "Leah," an essay by Wesker.
    Peter Bowering
  - "The Merchant"1977, October (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Play bill of a play by Wesker. Given at the John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts, Washington D.C.
- Magazine articles, 1954 - 1980, M1369 Series 2
  - "Londoner Revives Ancient Craft"1954 May-June (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Essay by Wesker in Norfolk Magazine, Norwich, Norfolk, U.K. Original and photocopy, with inscriptions to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "Two Lost Generations"1960, February (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Essay by Wesker in Definition, Quarterly Journal of Film Criticism, No 1, London. Note and inscription to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "The Modern Playwright," or "Mother Is It Worth It ?"1960 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    Essay by Wesker, Gemini, London
  - "Labor and the Arts"1960 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Essay by Wesker in Gemini, London,.
  - "The Secret Reins"1962, March (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Essay by Wesker in Encounter, Vol., XVIII, No. 3, London. Inscribed to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "The House" 1966, November (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Lecture by Wesker, given in Birmingham, in Encounter, Vol. XXVII, No. 5, London. Also contains a loose page of notepaper for Centre 42, Trade Union Council arts center. Note to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "The System and the Writer"[1970?] (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Interview with Wesker, New Theatre Magazine, Vol. XI, No. 2, Bristol, U.K.
  - "Conference in Tokyo"1971 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Article by Wesker in International Theatre Information, Winter, Paris.
  - "Last Letter to Aunty Sara from Arnold"1971, October (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Letter in The Garment Worker, Vol. 40, No. 10, London. Also photo of Aunt Sara. See also Box 3, Photographs and Drawings. Note and inscription to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "Bonne Feuilles" (French and English translations)1973, September-October (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Essay by Wesker on music and playwriting, in Musique de les Temps, No. 14 at St Michel de Provence, Forqualquier, France. Inscribed to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "A Time of Dying: A Sort of Short Story"1973 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Essay by Wesker in Jewish Quarterly, Vol. 21, Nos. 1-2, London. Contains reproduction of painting of Wesker. See also Box 3, Photographs and Drawings. Note and inscription to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "East End, My Cradle"1974, Novembr 24 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Essay by Wesker in Observer Sunday Magazine, with a painting of East End street by John Allin.
    John Allin
  - Arnold Wesker as a character in a comic book.1974 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    New Times, Class War Comics, No. 1, Brighton U. K. Also contains a drawing of Wesker taken from The London Times Colour Supplement, talks about Wesker's play "The Friends," produced in 1970. Explanatory note and inscription to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "Miseria de non essere Poeta" (Italian translation)1975 - 1976 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Lecture by Wesker given at Le Confereze dell' Associazione Culturale Italiana, in Genoa Turin, Milan, Rome. Published in Fasciolo 42. Inscribed to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "Min Mor" (Swedish translation)1977, February (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Essay by Wesker on his mother., in Femina, Helsingberg, Sweden. Early family photos reproduced. Inscription to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "Journal of 'The Journalists'."1977 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Journal entries by Wesker for his play "The Journalists," in Theatre Quarterly, London, Vol. VII, No. 26.
  - "Making the Case for Shylock"1977, November 26 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Interview with Wesker in The Nation, Vol. 225, No. 18. Inscribed to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "When I Was Your Age"1980 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Essay by Wesker in The School Times, Vol I, No. 2, London. Autographed by Wesker to his grandson, Jonathan Bickerbike.
    Jonathan Bickerbike
  - "Memorandum to Playwrights"1980, July (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Essay by Wesker in The Writer's News, London. Inscribed to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - Wesker, "Days in the Life of Arnold Wesker."1971, July (Box 4, Folder 77)
    In Ink, No l0, London.. Inscribed by Wesker with note to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - Wesker, "East End Roots" in Times Literary Supplement, London, 19751975 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Wesker, "The Merchant, " reviews, Arts Guardian, London, December 17, 19771977, December 17 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Wesker, "Not the Same," poem, Jewish Chronicle Literary Supplement, London, December 19791979, December (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Wesker, "The Confidence of Boughs," poem, Jewish Chronicle Literary Supplement, London, June 6, 19801980, June 6 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Wesker, "The Clouds Are Low," poem, Jewish Literary Supplement, London, December 26, 19801980, December 26 (Box 4, Folder 84)
- Critical Essays, 1968 - 1996, M1369 Series 3
  - Wesker, "Fears of Fragmentation," lecture on role of the artist, Tokyo.1968, October 18 (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - "Their Very Own and Golden City"1996, May 19 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Nine reviews of Wesker's play. Names of newspapers not given.
  - "A Letter to Mr. Arnold Wesker"1968 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    Open letter from Sato Susumo,Tokyo. Inscribed to Nathaniel Tarn.
    Susumo, Sato
  - "Casual Condemnations: A Brief Study of The Critic as Censor."1969? (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Article by Wesker in The Critic in the Theatre, London, No. 1, 1969.
  - " How Mr. Wesker's Plays End," 1970 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    Open letter from Sato Susumo, Tokyo
  - "Notes"1972 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    Review of Wesker's playwriting by Jack Cope, editor, in Contrast 29, South African Quarterly, Capetown, South Africa, Spring 1972. Includes photo of Wesker pasted on the Contents page. Inscribed to Nathaniel Tarn.
    Cope, Jack
  - "Chips with Everything,"1972 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    Wesker's play in Methuen's Study Aids, London, 1972. Also includes snapshot of Wesker. Insription and note to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "A Cretinue of Critics: An Open Letter to Harold Hobson"1972 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    Wesker in Drama: The Quarterly Theatre Review, No. 107, London. Winter 1972. With photo of Wesker on Pont Neuf, Paris 1956
  - "Wesker vs Taylor"1972 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    Plays and Players, London, Vol. 20, No. 2, November 1972. Contains photo of Wesker in Paris in l956. Inscribed to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "How to Cope with Criticism"1972 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    Wesker, in Plays and Players, Vol 20, No 3. London, 1972
  - "Critics Round Table"1976 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    Wesker, Seldes, Kalem, Wilson, New York Theater Review, discuss Wesker's play, "The Merchant," January 1976.
- Poems by Wesker, 1952 - 1979, M1369 Series 4
  - "The Poor" 1952 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    Wesker poem in Plan for Freedom and Progress, Vol. 21. No. 3, London, 1952. Inscription and note to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "The Book in My Hand"1960 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    Wesker poem in Overland Magazine, Melbourne Australia, No. 18, Winter/ Spring 1960. Inscription and note to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "My Child" and "The First Child"1961 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    Wesker poems in Overland Magazine, Melbourne, Australia No, 19, Summer 1960-61. Inscription and note to Nathaniel Tarn. (Also contains, Wesker's essay, "Oh ,Mother, Is it Really Worth It?" Labor and the Arts.)
  - "The First Child"1961 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    Wesker, poem in the sixties, London, Spring, l96l. Inscription and note to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - "Sitting Waiting for Aunty Anne"1971 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    1953 poem by Wesker, with photo of Aunty Anne, circa 1930, Stepney Words, London, l971, Inscription and note to Nathaniel Tarn. (Also contains a loose page letter to Wesker by Colin Searle.)
  - "It Was a Time of Feasts and Weddings"1978, April 14 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    Wesker poem in Piano, A Flowing Journal, Washington D. C., April l4, l978. Inscription and note to Nathaniel Tarn.
- Photographs and drawings, ca. 1920 - ca. 1981, M1369 Series 5
  - Colored broadsides about Wesker's work.1959 - 1969 (Box 4, Folder 79)
    Broadsides include comments on Wesker's plays, labor union activities, reviews etc..Times Educational Series, The Times Newspaper, Ltd.,
  - Photograph, by Barcelo of Barcelona, "Chips with Everything."1963 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    Spanish production. Incribed to Nathaniel Tarn.
  - Preliminary sketch for "The Old Ones," by Rudolph Heinrich, Munich, 19721972 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Three posters for three plays, "I'm Talking About Jerusalem", "Roots," and " Chicken Soup with Barley." Shaw Theatre, London, (1979?][1979?] (Box 4, Folder 82)
    Signed by Wesker with recepient marked on each.
  - Photo of Wesker's desk, with typewriter.n.d. (Box 3, Folder 63)
    Also draft of a letter or article. Camera Press Ltd., Peter Mitchell photographer.
  - Arnold Wesker's relativesn.d. (Box 3, Folder 64)
    Photograph, Wesker relatives.
  - "Some of My Third Cousins"[1920s?] (Box 3, Folder 65)
    Wesker's photographs ( "My Father's cousins") in the Soviet Union, late 1920s.
  - Photograph of poster of Cuban political figures1963 - 1964 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Photograph of Wesker pasted in.[1972?] (Box 3, Folder 67)
    Photo of Wesker, pasted in three quarter face against sculpture of Arnold Wesker by Francis Baruch, circa 1972
  - Press Cutting of phot of Wesker's mother, in Morning Star, London, September 1972.1972 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Photograph of Wesker on postcard. Postcard illustrated by John Allin painting of East End, London, 1974 ,with note to Nathaniel Tarn 19761976 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Drawing, copy of Rosenberg's "Ruth Lowy"[1981?] (Box 3, Folder 70)
- Miscellaneous, 1955 - 1988, M1369 Series 6
  - Letter to Wesker from John Lehmann, editor, The London Magazine, August 8, 19551955 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Schedule of Events, Battersea Arts Centre, U.K. September/October, 19881988 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Schedule of Events, The Old Bull Arts Centre, Barnet, Hertfordshire, U.K. Autumn 1988.1988. (Box 3, Folder 73)